Register of the Uncommon Knowledge Video Tapes
Hoover Institution Archives
- Individual Program Descriptions, 1996-2010 (Folder 1-60, 62-126, on shelf)
  - Series 900, 2004-2005
    - "A Line in the Test Tube: The Debate over Stem Cells" No. UK914, 2004 November 20 (Folder VHS, box 20; Betacam SP, box 41; Digital Betacam, box 100)
      Ramesh Ponnuru, media fellow, Hoover Institution and senior editor, National Review; and Irving Weissman, director, Cancer/Stem Cell Biology Institute, Stanford University School of Medicine. Proponents of embryonic stem cell research proclaim the potential of the research to find cures or treatments for many diseases such as Parkinson's and Alzheimer's. Opponents say the use and destruction of human embryos in the conduct of this research are immoral. In 2001, President Bush announced a ban on federal funding involving any new lines of embryonic stem cells. But calls to lift the ban continue, as do movements to increase funding at the state level. Which side of the debate is right? Is embryonic stem cell research ethical or not?
    - "An American Hiroshima: Preventing Nuclear Terrorism" No. UK915, 2004 November 20 (Folder VHS, box 21; Betacam SP, box 41)
      Graham Allison, Douglas Dillon professor of government, John F. Kennedy School of Government, Harvard University and author, Nuclear Terrorism: The Ultimate Preventable Catastrophe, and Scott Sagan, co-director, Center for International Security and Cooperation, Stanford University, and co-author, The Spread of Nuclear Weapons: A Debate Renewed. Many experts believe that it is almost inevitable that terrorists will soon have the ability to detonate a nuclear weapon in the heart of a major American city. How can we stop them? What are the specific threats that we face and how should we respond to them? Do we face a greater danger from nuclear weapons that may have been stolen from the former Soviet Union or from the clandestine efforts of rogue nuclear scientists? And if the threat has increased since 9/11, why hasn't the United States done more to contain it?
    - "Divorce, Transatlantic Style? The Future of Transatlantic Alliance" No. UK916, 2004 November 3 (Folder VHS, box 21; Betacam SP, box 41)
      Niall Ferguson, senior fellow, Hoover Institution and professor of history, Harvard University; Josef Joffe, research fellow, Hoover Institution and publisher-editor, Die Zeit; and Coit Blacker, director and senior fellow, Stanford Institute for International Studies. For forty-five years, the threat of conflict with the Soviet Union brought the United States and Western Europe into a tight partnership, most notably represented by the NATO military alliance. But with the Soviet Union gone and the European Union on the road to possible superpower status in its own right, does the transatlantic alliance have a future?
    - "Homeland Insecurity: Homeland Security" No. UK917, 2004 October 21 (Folder VHS, box 21; Betacam SP, box 41)
      Frances Edwards, director, Office of Emergency Services, City of San Jose, and Stephen Flynn, Jeanne J. Kirkpatrick senior fellow, Council on Foreign Relations, and author, America the Vulnerable: How Our Government Is Failing to Protect us from Terrorism. The terrorists behind the 9/11 attacks took advantage of vulnerabilities in a critical part of America's infrastructure - our air transportation system. Experts have pointed to similar vulnerabilities in our nation's food supply, our ports, and our chemical and nuclear facilities. Congress and the Bush administration responded to the threat of other such attacks by creating the Department of Homeland Security. But has the government done enough? What more should we be doing to defend against potentially devastating domestic terrorist attacks? And just how much can we do without infringing on our freedom and way of life?
    - "Great Expectations: The Future of the European Union" No. UK918, 2004 October 25 (Folder VHS, box 21; Betacam SP, box 42; Digital Betacam, box 100)
      John O'Sullivan, editor, National Interest, and Adrian Wooldridge, Washington correspondent, Economist. For some six decades, the continent of Europe has enjoyed remarkable peace and prosperity. What role has the European Union played in this success? And what role should the European Union play in the future? According to some European leaders, the purpose of the European Union is to create a superpower capable of counterbalancing the United States. Is the goal of a superpower Europe a good idea? Is it even possible?
    - "Who Needs the United Nations? Reforming the United Nations" No. UK919, 2004 October 25 (Folder VHS, box 21; Betacam SP, box 42; Digital Betacam, box 100)
      Victor Davis Hanson, Martin and Illie Anderson senior fellow, Hoover Institution, and Jane Wales, president and CEO, World Affairs Council of Northern California. In 2003, the secretary general of the United Nations appointed a 16-member commission to assess the threats to worldwide security in the twenty-first century. The commission came back with a number of recommendations for reforming the UN itself. Is this institution so important that it must be preserved and reformed? Or, given its lack of response to the crisis in Iraq, the ongoing nuclear crises in North Korea and Iran, and the humanitarian crisis in the Sudan, is the UN beyond reform? Perhaps it has outlasted its usefulness.
    - "Commanding Heights: American Empire" No. UK920, 2004 November 3 (Folder VHS, box 21; Betacam SP, box 42; Digital Betacam, box 100)
      Niall Ferguson, senior fellow, Hoover Institution, professor of history, Harvard University, and author, Colossus: The Price of America's Empire, and Ivan Eland, senior fellow, Independent Institute and author, The Empire Has No Clothes: U.S. Foreign Policy Exposed. Since the end of the cold war, the United States has been the world's only superpower, accounting for 43 percent of the world's military expenditures. During this time, America has led major interventions in Kosovo, Afghanistan, and Iraq. Are the United States and the world better off when America follows a unilateral, interventionist foreign policy? Or should the United States reduce its overseas presence and instead emphasize international cooperation?
    - "Latin America Goes South: Political Reform in Latin America" No. UK921, 2004 October 12 (Folder VHS, box 21; Betacam SP, box 42; Digital Betacam, box 101)
      Stephen Haber, Peter and Helen Bing senior fellow, Hoover Institution and A. A. and Jeanne Welch Milligan professor, Stanford University, and Alvaro Vargas Llosa, research fellow, Independent Institute and author, Liberty for Latin America: How to Undo Five Hundred Years of State Oppression. Over the last quarter century, Latin America appears to have made remarkable political and economic progress - an undeniable shift towards democratic government and free market economics. Yet during the last five years, several Latin American countries have experienced one political and economic crisis after another. Why? Have democratic and free market reforms failed Latin America? Or are enduring problems of governmental structure still to blame?
    - "Rial Politik: Defusing the Iranian Nuclear Crisis" No. UK922, 2004 December 13 (Folder VHS, box 21; Betacam SP, box 42; Digital Betacam, box 101)
      Larry Diamond, senior fellow, Hoover Institution and professor, political science, Stanford University, and Abbas Milani, research fellow, Hoover Institution. Iran - the same country that took American diplomats hostage twenty-five years ago and whose leaders often refer to the United States as the "Great Satan" - may be on the verge of developing nuclear weapons. How worried should we be? What can the United States do, if anything, to defuse the threat of a nuclear-armed Iran? Is a military response feasible? Or should the United States focus on strengthening the movement for democratic reform within Iran?
    - "The Electoral College's Excellent Adventure: Should We Abolish the Electoral College?" No. UK923, 2004 December 13 (Folder VHS, box 21; Betacam SP, box 42; Digital Betacam, box 101)
      Jack Rakove, Coe professor of history and American studies, Stanford University, and Tara Ross, author, Enlightened Democracy: The Case for the Electoral College. As required by the Constitution, the president of the United States is elected not by the national popular vote but by the vote of the Electoral College. In the Electoral College, each state receives as many votes as it has members of Congress. Because every state has two senators and is guaranteed at least one House member, votes of small states count more heavily than votes of large states. Has the Electoral College served the nation well? Or should it be abolished and replaced by a system in which every vote counts the same?
    - "Monkey Business: Evolution and Intelligent Design" No. UK924, 2005 January 14 (Folder VHS, box 21; Betacam SP, box 42; Digital Betacam, box 101)
      In October 2004, the school board in the small town of Dover, Pennsylvania, ordered its high school biology teachers to preface classes on evolution with the statement: "Darwin's Theory is a theory not a fact. Gaps in the theory exist for which there is no evidence." As an alternative to evolution, the school board suggested "intelligent design," a theory holding that life on earth could not have developed at random. Are there gaps in the theory of evolution that undermine its credibility? What should we make of "intelligent design"? And just what should we be teaching our children about the development of life on earth? Peter Robinson speaks with Massimo Pigliucci and Jonathan Wells.
    - "Making the Grade: The No Child Left Behind Act" No. UK925, 2005 January 14 (Folder VHS, box 21; Betacam SP, box 42; Digital Betacam, box 102)
      In 2001, President Bush signed into law the No Child Left Behind Act, a bipartisan effort to mandate national education standards and increase federal funding of education. At the time, critics on both sides of the political spectrum were troubled by the expansion of federal power over education that the act represented and by the education standards the act mandated. Now, nearly half a decade later, has No Child Left Behind been a success? If not, how should it be reformed? Peter Robinson speaks with John E. Chubb and Martin Carnoy.
    - "A Healthy Debate: Health Care Reform" No. UK926, 2005 February 1 (Folder VHS, box 21; Betacam SP, box 42; Digital Betacam, box 102)
      The United States leads the developed world in spending on health care, at nearly 15 percent of our GDP. But based on measures such as life expectancy at birth, Americans receive a lower level of care than do the citizens of many countries that spend less. What's wrong with health care in America? And how should we fix it? Peter Robinson speaks with John F. Cogan and Alain Enthoven.
    - "Land of Lincoln: Abraham Lincoln and American History" No. UK927, 2005 February 1 (Folder VHS, box 21; Betacam SP, box 42; Digital Betacam, box 102)
      Henry Ford once said that "history is more or less bunk. We want to live in the present and the only history that is worth a tinker's dam is the history we make today." Do Americans care about history or not? Journalist Andrew Ferguson discusses America's relationship with its own history using the continuing fascination with Abraham Lincoln as a case study.
    - "The French Kiss-Off: The History of French and American Relations" No. UK928, 2005 February 11 (Folder VHS, box 21; Betacam SP, box 42; Digital Betacam, box 102)
      Is France America's oldest friend or its oldest enemy? Americans are taught that the United States owes its very independence to France-that if the French hadn't helped us during the Revolutionary War, we would still be part of the British Empire. Was this assistance the beginning of a long and close friendship between France and America or an anomaly in an otherwise contentious relationship? Peter Robinson speaks with John Miller and Robert Paxton Mellon.
    - "The Bottomless Well: Are We Running out of Energy?" No. UK929, 2005 February 11 (Folder VHS, box 22; Betacam SP, box 43; Digital Betacam, box 103)
      Many petroleum experts predict that world oil production will peak by the end of the decade. Will the United States soon be entering a period of worsening energy shortages and soaring energy costs? And, if so, what should the government to do about it? Or will the ever-improving technological efficiencies of the free market provide access to virtually endless sources of new energy? Peter Robinson speaks with Peter Huber and Jonathan Koomey.
    - "Give Me Civil Liberties or Give Me...Safety? Should the Patriot Act Be Renewed?" No. UK930, 2005 February 11 (Folder VHS, box 22; Betacam SP, box 43; Digital Betacam, box 103)
      In late 2001, in response to the terrorist attacks of 9/11, the Bush administration proposed the USA Patriot Act, which gave law enforcement agencies expanded surveillance and intelligence-gathering powers. Congress overwhelmingly approved the Patriot Act on the condition that most provisions of the act would expire in 2005. President Bush now wants all provisions of the act extended. Should they be? Or are the provisions dangerous and unnecessary infringements on our civil liberties? Peter Robinson speaks with Jenny Martinez and John Yoo.
    - "Tort and Retort: Tort Reform" No. UK931, 2005 February 25 (Folder VHS, box 22; Betacam SP, box 43; Digital Betacam, box 103)
      During the 2004 presidential campaign, one principal plank of George W. Bush's domestic platform was reforming tort law, which includes class action lawsuits, asbestos liability, and medical malpractice liability. President Bush believes that tort law as it now stands permits trial lawyers to take advantage of good companies, driving up the costs of doing business for everyone. Others believe that existing tort law allows consumers to protect themselves against bad companies. Which is it? And should President Bush be given the tort reforms he wants? Peter Robinson speaks with David Davenport and Alan Morrison.
    - "Inalienable Rites? Gay Marriage in the Courts" No. UK932, 2005 March 25 (Folder VHS, box 22; Betacam SP, box 43; Digital Betacam, box 103)
      On March 14, 2005, a California Superior Court judge ruled that the state's ban on same-sex marriage violated the state constitution. Although the decision is certain to be appealed up to the California Supreme Court, California may now be on the road to joining Massachusetts in legalizing gay marriage. Did the Superior Court judge decide correctly? Just how compelling are the constitutional arguments for and against gay marriage? Peter Robinson speaks with Terry Thompson and Tobias Wolff.
    - "Hitch-cocked: A Conversation with Christopher Hitchens" No. UK933, 2005 March 25 (Folder VHS, box 22; Betacam SP, box 43)
      Journalist Christopher Hitchens discusses neoconservatives and the left, his break with The Nation magazine over his support of the war in Iraq, and his tour of the three members of the "axis of evil."
    - "Pay It Forward: Social Security Reform" No. UK934, 2005 April 15 (Folder VHS, box 22; Betacam SP, box 43; Digital Betacam, box 104)
      In making Social Security reform a top priority of his second term, President George W. Bush has emphasized two points: first, that, without changes, our Social Security system will be bankrupt by 2042 and, second, that a key element of reform must be creating private accounts to allow workers to invest a portion of their payroll taxes in stocks and bonds. Is the president right on both counts? Peter Robinson speaks with John Cogan and Alan Auerbach.
    - "Alexander the Great: Alexander Hamilton" No. UK935, 2005 April 15 (Folder VHS, box 22; Betacam SP, box 43; Digital Betacam, box 104)
      Alexander Hamilton, the first secretary of the treasury, may today be better known for his death in a duel with Aaron Burr, than for the role he played as a founder of the nascent United States. His vision of a federal, mercantile nation was in opposition to Thomas Jefferson's vision of an agrarian society. Who won this battle of ideas and why? Just what is the enduring legacy of Alexander Hamilton? Peter Robinson speaks with Ron Chernow.
    - "Speak No Evil: Freedom of Speech on Campus" No. UK936, 2005 April 15 (Folder VHS, box 22; Betacam SP, box 43; Digital Betacam, box 104)
      According to recent polls, instructors at American universities are overwhelmingly liberal: 72 percent of faculty members describe themselves as liberal, whereas only 15 percent call themselves conservative. Some critics charge that this ideological imbalance has created a code of political correctness that inhibits freedom of inquiry and expression in our universities. Is this true? And if so, what should be done, or can be done, about it? Peter Robinson speaks with David Horowitz and Graham Larkin.
    - "Love and Marriage: Marriage in Modern America" No. UK937, 2005 April 18 (Folder VHS, box 22; Betacam SP, box 43; Digital Betacam, box 104)
      Most people would agree that families and the institution of marriage are not what they were fifty years ago. Many couples are cohabiting without marriage, and many children are being raised in single-parent homes or other nontraditional family arrangements. Is the traditional model of marriage and family superior to these other arrangements, as some would argue? If so, why have marriage and family relationships changed so much over the past half-century? And what should the government do, if anything, to strengthen families and the institution of marriage? Peter Robinson speaks with Jennifer Roback Morse and Stephanie Coontz.
    - "Holding Court: The Legacy of the Rehnquist Court" No. UK938, 2005 May 26 (Folder VHS, box 22; Betacam SP, box 43)
      William H. Rehnquist has served as chief justice of the United States Supreme Court for nineteen years, the longest tenure of a chief justice in a century. How has the Rehnquist Court responded to the key constitutional issues of our times? What will be the philosophical legacy of the man himself? And who will miss him more, liberals or conservatives? Peter Robinson speaks with Kathleen Sullivan and John Yoo.
    - "The Best Defense: Preventive War" No. UK939, 2005 May 26 (Folder VHS, box 22; Betacam SP, box 43)
      In 2002, the Bush administration published a new National Security Strategy, which argued that, in the twenty-first century, it was necessary for the United States not merely to defend itself but to use military force to prevent threats such as terrorist attacks and weapons of mass destruction. Is preventive force just? Is it effective? And what can the biggest example of this doctrine in action, the war in Iraq, tell us about the future of preventive force? Peter Robinson speaks with Victor Davis Hanson, Anne-Marie Slaughter, and Stephen Stedman.
  - Web, 2006
    - "The Constitution and the War" No. WUK06_01, 2006 October 29 (Folder Digital Betacam, box 105; DVD MPEG4, box 119)
      Where should we draw the line between civil liberties and national security in the "war on terror"? Are we even at war, and if so, what are the constitutional limits to presidential war powers? Has the Bush administration gone too far in the electronic surveillance of citizens and the coercive interrogation of suspected terrorists and enemy combatants? Richard Epstein and John Yoo, both widely regarded as strict constitutional constructionists, take decidedly different positions on these questions.
    - "Economic Growth In India and China" No. WUK06_02, 2006 November 27 (Folder Digital Betacam, box 105; DVD MPEG4, box 119)
      According to Michael Spence, "We are entering a period in which the two most populous countries in the world are the fastest-growing countries in the world-and the fastest-growing countries in the history of the world." How have India and China done it, and what problems do they face as they seek to sustain this growth? What threats do these two economic powers pose to the United States, and what strategies should guide our relations with them?
    - "Bring Back The Draft" No. WUK06_03, 2006 December 12 (Folder Digital Betacam, box 105; DVD MPEG4, box 119)
      Under President Nixon, in 1973 the United States abolished the draft, moving to an all-volunteer armed forces. Now some-most notably New York congressman Charles Rangel, chairman of the House Ways and Means Committee-have called for a reinstatement of the draft. Is this a good idea? What lessons from history can we call on to help answer this question? And what impact would the reinstatement of the draft have on society as a whole and the military in particular? Peter Robinson speaks with David Kennedy and Edwin Meese.
    - "The Iraq Study Group" No. WUK06_04, 2006 December 12 (Folder Digital Betacam, box 105; DVD MPEG4, box 119)
      As one of the prominent conservative members of the Iraq Study Group, Edwin Meese has drawn withering criticism from the right for the group's recommendations-the National Review calling their final report "dressed-up surrender in Iraq." Just what does the report say about the situation in Iraq, what to do about troop levels, and a "new diplomatic offensive in the Middle East"? Meese takes on the key points and their critics and offers a strong defense of the positions staked out by the Iraq Study Group.
  - Web, 2007
    - "Inside The Economist Magazine" No. WUK07_01, 2007 February 5 (Folder Digital Betacam, box 105; DVD MPEG4, box 119)
      From his vantage point as the editor-in-chief of one of the most respected news magazines in the world, John Micklethwait discusses how this 150-year-old "newspaper" maintains its leadership position in the increasing precarious environment of print journalism. Along the way, he offers his job performance evaluation of Tony Blair and George Bush and is challenged to defend his previous assertion that "The conservative movement has become the dominant intellectual force in American politics."
    - "The Cold War" No. WUK07_02, 2007 April 23 (Folder Digital Betacam, box 106; DVD MPEG4, box 119)
      John O'Sullivan explores three competing explanations for the causes of the cold war and the three fundamental explanations for its end. Along the way, he offers in the Soviet Union a cogent analysis of the roles played by Mikhail Gorbachev and by Ronald Reagan, Margaret Thatcher, and Pope John Paul II in the West.
    - "How Can The GOP Get Its Groove Back?" No. WUK07_03, 2007 April 23 (Folder DVD MPEG4, box 119)
      Governor Haley Barbour reflects on the current state of the Grand Old Party and what it will take for it to regain its prominence in American politics. What did the GOP do right in the mid-nineties to capture a majority in the House of Representatives for the first time in forty years, and what is it doing wrong today? And how can the party adapt the conservatism of Ronald Reagan to the current issues of the day?
    - "Fred Thompson, The Candidate" No. WUK07_04, 2007 June 11 (Folder miniDV, box 118; miniDV, box 118; DVD MPEG4, box 119)
      Hoover Institution fellow, Peter Robinson, speaks with Fred Thompson about his candidacy for President of the United States. Robinson delves into the key issues facing America today, the politics of running for president, and the source of Thompson's conservative views.
    - "Land of Lincoln" No. WUK07_05, 2007 July 10 (Folder Digital Betacam, box 106; DVD MPEG4, box 119)